I am so excited to introduce our featured lab manager for today, Nicola Rennie. Nicola,
would you like to say hello and introduce yourself?
I can. Hello, I'm Nicola. I do a lot of data viz stuff. I've been using R for about 10
years, and I'm very excited to be doing some TidyTuesday visualizations live today.
Yes, I'm so excited. Okay, well, this is the place where we share screens and do stuff. So,
Nicola, I'm going to say, take it away. And while you are sharing your screen, I will prime
everybody by saying Nicola is going to show us her process of how she works through a TidyTuesday
visualization. But we only have an hour here. And really, we only have like, what, 50 minutes,
and we're going to be asking questions. So quite obviously, she can't go through her entire process,
but she is going to be sharing some of the ways that she thinks, some of the tools she's developed
over the years. She'll talk about how long she's been doing this, how long she spends on stuff like
this. So get your question asking, typing fingers ready. All right, take it away, Nicola.
Awesome. Thank you. So yeah, if you don't know what TidyTuesday is already, it's a super awesome
sort of resource. So basically, a new dataset is released every week, every Tuesday. Although
sometimes it's a Sunday, sometimes it's a Monday, you never know. And the idea is that you make
something with it and share it and share your code with other people. I started doing TidyTuesday.
It was my COVID lockdown 2021 project. Other people took up baking or cycling or whatever.
For some reason, I got into TidyTuesday. So there's a GitHub repo. And if you scroll down
in the GitHub repo, you can see all the datasets from each week. So this week, the dataset is on
Twin Cities. So if you go into the readme for a specific week, you get a little bit of information
about what the data is about, where it's from. You get some instructions for how to load it into
R, Python, Julia, and their CSV files, if you really want those. And there's some really nice
data dictionaries that explain what all the variable names mean. And those are really,
really helpful. So this week's data is all about Twin Cities, so links between different cities
around the world. So there's actually two datasets this week. So one of them is all about the actual
cities. So you've got an ID, the name of the city, coordinates of where it is, what country it's in,
and continent. And then the second dataset is the actual links between them. So it's just
two columns and start and end point of the links. So I'm going to jump over to R
and see if we can start making some things. Awesome. And I asked everybody if they can both
see your screen and hear you clearly. And everybody so far has given me a thumbs up.
Everybody, if there is a point in time when you need things to be zoomed in a little bit more
on Nicola's screen, please let us know. Thank you for the thumbs up and zoom. All right, great.
Nice. All right. So I have all of my tidy Tuesday visualizations from the last five years
all live in one GitHub repo, which is fairly nicely structured.
One of the things that I started making to try and help save myself some time was some template
files. Because when you're doing, whether it's visualizations or analysis or whatever it is,
you end up doing the same thing or very similar things week after week. And I didn't want to just
keep typing out the same things every week. So I made myself a little R package, which has some
templates in it. So if I go to that R package and do templates, you can see I've got a couple here.
So I have this use tidy Tuesday template. And what I just need to put in here is the date.
So it's today's date, which is 2026, 5th, and it's the 12th. So if I run that, that creates
a whole bunch of files for me. It creates an R script and a readme file. So if I open these up,
you can see it's in here. So it creates this folder here and it makes a readme file,
which I will open as well. Okay. So it just has some space for a title and loads in the chart
that we will make hopefully in this hour. And then this is the R script that it generates.
So I'll talk you through this a little bit first, but we'll kind of go into more depth
as we go through. So we load all the packages to start off with, basically the entire tidyverse.
I also use the show text package for text. I love the show text package because you can load
like Google fonts, which means you never have to worry about trying to install fonts on your
own laptop or try to give other people instructions for loading fonts on their laptop. Also got a
couple of packages for doing some fancy text. So like some bold highlighting or like color text.
We've got glue for sticking together variables and text. And we've got the ggview package,
which is super useful for previewing your plots at the same size and resolution that you want to
save them at. So if you've ever done that thing where you're like spending ages tinkering with
your plot and like making it look really pretty and perfect, and then you use ggsave and it just
like, it's a complete mess and it looks nothing like the preview you had in RStudio, ggview is
really good for that and I'll show you how it works. So the other sections in this
template are basically like to load in the data and the templates files are put in the correct
date and stuff. This is loading some fonts from the show text package. I've got some defaults
in there so that if I'm like having a busy day and I don't have time to pick out fancy fonts, I've got
something that I know looks all right. I've got some default colors. Again, if I'm busy then I'll
use those. I've got some sort of like setup because every time I'm making a chart it's like almost
always got title, subtitle, caption and all of that. So just like prep those variables ahead of time.
And then I've got kind of like a theme that's set up and it's all kind of written out rather than
being like in a personalized theme function so that it's easier to edit one bit of it for a
particular chart. And then I've got some code at the bottom to save it in the correct place so I
never need to worry about figuring out where I'm supposed to be saving stuff. Hey Nicola, I
have a question because we are on fonts right now on the screen. Rory has a question that resonates
with me too which is do show text and system fonts do different things? He says because fonts
and ggplot scare me and honestly same. I stay away from anything that's not standard because I'm scared.
I'm like this isn't gonna work. So they can do the same thing but they can also do
different things. So system fonts is really good for finding fonts that you have installed
on your computer. That works great if you are just making it yourself but if you're
collaborating with other people and one of you is on Windows and one of you is on
Linux and you're trying to use some Microsoft font, then you have to give instructions
for how you install fonts. Whereas this sort of font at Google, I mean as long as you have
an internet connection it just sort of downloads it from Google so you don't have to worry about
whether you have that font, whether your collaborator has that font. It just kind of loads
it in for you. You can load local fonts with show text as well if you do have something
special or different that you want to use. It's kind of incentivizing to stick with Google
fonts though because then you kind of can't get it wrong, right? Yeah, the only time I've like
it's not worked is when I've been on a train and there's been like no wi-fi and your script
doesn't run because you can't connect to the internet. But that's like a weird, it's a very
niche problem I think. Yes, all right, awesome, thank you. Nice, but yeah fonts in R are super
like tricky and weird. So the only thing I'm going to grab from the R for Data Science tidyTD
repo is this little bit of code here to kind of load in the specific data sets. So if I just run
all of this, it's kind of like when you run tidyTD, the RTT load, it's like downloading those
CSV files from GitHub. And then now I have two data sets. I have one called cities, right? So
it's got that like unique ID, the name of the city, coordinates, country and country code,
and continent. And links looks a little bit confusing but it's just the ID for different
countries and source and target just says that there's a link between those two countries. So
I'm also just gonna run this in the background and then kind of start to think about what on earth
I'm gonna plot with this data. It is a really nice data set, like it's not super big like in
terms of number of rows or columns but there's so many things I kind of want to look at with this
data. So one of the things I would quite like to look at is whether you can connect every country
in the world through like one giant loop of like these twin cities. Other things you could look at
is like which country is the most connected. So you could do some sort of like global map
in color based on how connected they are. What I kind of want to look at is how
like connected the world is to each other in terms of how close things are. So like is a city
in Europe more likely to be connected to other cities in Europe? So what I'm gonna, my brain's
sort of thinking in terms of chart type is something maybe like a Sankey diagram or a chord diagram.
But then you kind of have to choose what level you do it at. If you do that at the country level
it's just, I think it's just going to look like a big pile of spaghetti because there's too many
countries and there's just going to be lots and lots of lines. At the same time I think if you
do it a continent level there's like, that might work. There's like, I think there's six in the
data set. So that will probably work okay. I think what I'm going to do though is pick one city
and then sort of look at how connected that is. Okay so I'm gonna have a little look first of all
at what like list of cities we have. So actually if I just look at the data set. So you can use
the view function in R and then just kind of like sort them and have a little look. I think like
when I'm doing tidy Tuesday quite a lot I quite often pick like cities or countries that I know
like are some way connected to me personally because then you find out like interesting
things about like where you live or that kind of thing. So I want to see if I start with cities
and then filter the country code to be GB. So we'll have a look at what's in the UK and then
I quite often pipe that into view at the end. So you get this nice kind of human readable look
and then I can browse through all the cities in the UK that we might focus on. I'm going to
go Edinburgh because that's where I live. So purely self-serving. So
that's giving me one row of the data and the thing that I'm really interested in then
is going to be this ID column. So I'm just gonna grab that. Okay I think what I'm also
thinking at the moment is this is something that I would quite like to parameterise.
So the idea is that you can type in whatever city you want and at the end you will get the plot for
your chosen city. I like that. Thinking ahead. Yes I'm trying to think ahead. It's one of these
things with like a really big data set when you pick like one tiny little aspect of it
the chances of someone else picking that really same specific aspect is probably quite small.
We have at least one other person who sees their hometown,
Shirakawa. Satoshi says I see my hometown. Did anybody else see theirs? I did not see mine yet.
All right so I've got my ID. So what I need to do now is go into this links data set
and pick out like all the links that relate to this city ID. This one's a little bit weird
because the the order of the source and the target doesn't matter at all. So I need to filter it when
either the source is equal to the city ID or when the target is equal to the city ID.
Yeah that didn't work. That's because I said or not and. There you go. All right so I've got 11
links and you can see that like some of them are in the first column and some of them are in the
second column and that's um it's like a little bit annoying. So I'm actually going to grab them.
So I want to get the ID. Let's do if else. So if the source ID is equal to my city ID
then what I actually want is the other one and then vice versa. Okay so now yeah now this column
is all of the like IDs of the other cities that it's linked with
and that's the only thing I actually want. I use select all the time to like tidy up because I
really hate having extra columns um that I'm not interested in kind of hanging around in my data.
Purely personal choice. But now I can join this with the city's data by the ID right and that's
my sort of like I guess tidy final data set. So I have 11 cities that are all linked to
my Chubbledon city editor and I've got one city that's not linked to my Chubbledon city
editor and I've got like all the information on them.
So I always save this as like plot data. It's not the most imaginative name but I do it every time.
I'm going to skip over the text pictures now because quite often it's kind of like
I actually write it at the end once you figure out what your plot is of and what you want to say.
So now I need to think a little bit about how I want to visualise this.
We have some votes for 3D bar charts jokingly in the discord.
No, no, no, no.
Don't listen.
I think what I really want to hear is like a sunburst diagram. So like in the middle you're
going to have that chosen city and then you will have all the cities it's connected to
then all of the countries they're in and then all of the continents they're in.
I'm kind of thinking if you colour by continent then you can see like quite clearly
like which continent is going to dominate and whether that's the same as the continent that
your chosen city is in. So sunburst diagrams are like
kind of like I guess like a circular tree map and or kind of like stacked doughnut charts.
So there are different ways to make them.
So one of the things I quite often do at this point is if I'm thinking about a chart that
I know I've made before I quite often like go and look at the code for that chart and just
like copy and paste it and then edit it rather than just copy and paste it and then edit it.
And then edit it rather than trying to write it from scratch every time.
So I have a little shiny app that grabs all of my Tidy Tuesday plots from
that repository and you can kind of search by package. You can also search by name which I
appreciate is not the most useful. But I remember doing a sunburst chart on Australian Frogs
for previous Tidy Tuesday. Good memory.
So this is what sunburst chart is and I have links to the code. So when I click on this it
just opens and then I get the code. Oh my gosh the benefits of good documentation for your own stuff.
You have to learn the hard way I think. I still curse 2021 me for their terrible file naming
system. But yeah so this I can see like how did I make it the last time and the last time I made
it in a really weird way. Okay I know why I did this. Sometimes it takes a while for me to remember
why I did certain things. So normally if I was making a sunburst diagram I would probably use
the ggforce package which has like geom arc bar. Yeah. But I wanted to make it interactive so it
had these little tooltips and that doesn't work with the giraffe package. So I think I remade
instead of arcs I made them all as polygons. I'm sorry I think you mean the ggiraffe package. Yes.
I never know. I never know. It's totally giraffe. It says it in the documentation.
But I will never not call it ggiraffe. Yeah I called it ggiraffe for like years and then
Kara Thompson showed me the hex sticker and it was a picture of a giraffe and we were both kind of like
oh that makes sense. It is 100% giraffe. Okay we can move on. So this one was a little while
ago and I think it was before a newer version of ggplot2 came out. So I think previously if
you wanted to make like pie charts or donut charts in ggplot2 you could make like a bar chart and
then use a chord polar which kind of like pushes it into a circle. The problem with that is that
like putting annotations and stuff on it is a nightmare because their coordinate system is
just goes crazy and you don't know where any points actually are. But the newer versions of
ggplot2 have like a chord radial which I think is basically just fixes that issue. So I'm gonna
attempt that. So what do I want? First of all I need to figure out for every given- so I'm gonna
have three layers on my radial chart, my sunburst chart. I'm gonna have like cities, countries and
then continents. So I need to take my bot data and then group it by one of the regions. So let's just
start with city which is actually in the data city is down as name but I know I'm gonna keep
typing city if I mean city. So I'm gonna rename that. So group by city. Rename it. Yes. I'm all
about renaming something. I'll spend more time fixing my own typos than it will just fixing it.
So I want to count up the number of each city which okay there should just be one.
So I then did that and then I need to keep
the city the number and because I want to color by continent I need to keep that in the data.
So this is what I need. Now I want to do the same code for country and continent so I'm gonna stick
this as a function to save me wrangling lots of little data sets. So it's gonna be a function of
region. All right. Grab that in there. We might have crashed your Shiny app.
They give it the hug of death Nicola. So the Shiny app it will take a while to load
because it's actually it's deployed with WebR so you're not crashing my Shiny app you're
crashing your own browser. Good. Okay. That's good news actually. So it's posted in your own
browser. Give it a second and let it load. It does take a little while just because it's like
WebR and it's kind of loading a bunch of packages in the background. Yeah.
Okay. So yeah I've got this little function here which takes like a region level so that will take
city country or continent as an input and it will return me a data set that looks a little
bit like this. You may or may not have seen this like weird curly bracket notation before.
It's like a weird sort of tidy eval thing that lets you put variable names in without
quotation marks essentially. Yeah I call it a double hug. Yes. So if I do something like
region data of country I get that right. So I still have the country the number and if I do
continent I think it's gonna give me some duplicates. So let's stick distinct in there.
I don't want to count them all twice. Okay. So that's a nice quick way of getting my data sets.
So start actually making a chart. So I love that you have just chord radial
floating down. Yeah just waiting. I'm like I will need that in a moment. Don't delete it.
You'll have to type it again. Okay. So I want to do geom call. So my data is going to be
this region data. I'm going to start with city
and then mapping is going to be a little bit weird. So I think your x variables I want to be
n and y I want to be like one and then fill is equal to continent.
I think it's not going to do what I want. Okay. That sort of looks correct.
And then if I add chord radial. Okay. It's got a weird gap here which I don't want.
I always use like expand equals false in like most of my charts because I don't I don't like the
weird extra space. So this. Okay. This is kind of made a pie chart. That's
we can't. We made a pie chart by accident. Accidentally made some pie charts. Okay.
But this this should go away. So if I switch y to 2 that should stack another one on top of it.
And I should have region data is equal to country. Okay. This is looking better.
And then if I do one more this is going to be like continent and is move that up to three.
Okay. I think the actually three. Okay. That starting to look better.
I like this. Now we're getting closer to like a dartboard. Oh but you know what I saw we had a
question that might benefit us to do well before we get too far away from your d player query.
And it was from Nathan saying can you say why you used mutate rather than summarize.
Yes. Because I want to keep continent in there. So if I normally only wanted to
like when you summarize it will get rid of everything that you haven't kind of grouped by.
But yeah I'm using mutate because I want to I want to color by continent. So it needs to
stick around. So that's the only reason I'm kind of using mutate there. Excellent. Thank you.
All right. Okay. So I want to get rid of this pie chart thing in the middle.
So I want to do here is if I filter the city's data to get the city
chosen city. So and then the X value is going to be all of them. So it's within number of rows.
Right. Yes. Yes I did. I equals equals.
There we go. The most commonly made mistake for me in R. Absolutely. Did you mean double.
Did you mean. Yeah. Yes I did. Thank you. All right. That sort of looks.
What I mean like is a rough idea. One thing that's a little bit weird is that you can't see
like the different cities because there's no outlines. So I'm gonna if I say color
is equal to my text color. Does this help. Yeah. So that and I'm just going to copy and paste that
in here. So now it's a little bit easier to see that like you have your one city that you picked
you have your one city that you picked in the middle. There's like three four seven cities
in seven countries that are all in Europe which means we now get to do the fun part which is
like making it look pretty. Yeah. I think it's it's great to see that you still have all of the
like random bits that are around right. Like you haven't like theme voided anything. You're just
like leave them there. It's fine. We're going to we're going to get there. Yeah. I quite often
like theme void is great for making kind of charts like this in maps but quite often I leave it to
the very end because it can really help with like positioning annotations and things if you can be
like I want to go there and you can see what those coordinates are. And if you are working with a
grid I made the mistake one time in a very big project of just sort of theme voiding from the
beginning and not showing my my indexes basically on the side and I couldn't figure out why my plot
was upside down and it's just because I didn't have the visual cue of going oh because my numbers
are backwards. Yeah. Yeah. Don't do that to yourself. Yeah. Don't do that. Keep anything
that might be helpful until the end. So this I guess this all sometimes feels a little bit like
cheating when you use a template so you can just stick a plus on the end and then fire in all of
the sort of template like theme stuff that I had. So I tend to just run it and see what it looks like.
One thing that you might notice one I guess the text is like slightly different size and also
it's opened in this viewer tab and that's because it has this plus canvas thing on the end and that's
from ggview. So here you can say I want it to be like 7 by 5 dpi is 300 which matches with ggsave
and set the background color of like the whole area which means that when like if you use ggsave
to save this that is what it will look like. It shows you exactly as it will be and it's like a
quite nice way to play around with some different sizes. So I think actually for this chart I
probably want it to be portrait. If I put some text above it and get rid of that legend.
I'm gonna do that just now. Legend.position equals none.
Okay yeah all right. I am gonna switch this to theme void to get rid of all of the
stuff I don't want and I'm gonna add an annotation
to put like the name of the chosen city right in the middle.
Middle of our dartboard. Yeah. Okay so or wait chosen city we parameterized.
Yes we did. I'm using we generously here.
So it's gonna be label equals chosen city and it's gonna be text and add that on at the end.
All right okay so it's not super in the middle but it's that's all right. Okay what else do I
want to do? So one thing I want to do is I want to get rid of the little white gaps between them.
A little bit annoying. So in ggplot2 the width of columns is 0.9 not one. So let's get rid of that
and then I'm going to colors. I don't like the ggplot2 default colors.
Oh sorry Hadley.
Yeah I'm gonna let's use something else. I quite often use our carto color because
they have this kind of like nice combination of like being accessible and being quite good colors
but also looking quite nice. So I use them quite a lot and I'm going to define a color palette
from there. The other thing I want to do is like map continents to colors kind of ahead of time
because you can see there's only four in this chart but there's actually six values.
So if you were to choose a different city then the colors might switch order which is not great.
So you would kind of recycle right? Yeah or like you would like I think they go alphabetically so
oh if you they might just shift around which is a little bit weird. So
I need one color for every unique value in the continent.
Okay name so continents this color palette is gonna be our carto color
carto palette n is going to be the length of continents
and okay if I just go here you have to give the names of the palette you want.
It's going to be from here.
dplyr, ggplot2, Shiny, systemfonts
so it will use the same combination of color and content regardless of which order they appear in
so if I do in here like scale fill manual values equals my color palette
all right I get that okay
what I quite often do with kind of like instead of a legend is I use like color text in the legend
so you'd have like a nice sentence that writes out all the different continent names that are
and the color that applies in the chart so to do that you can use I think you can use marquee
but I've been kind of using ggtext for so long that that is kind of my default so the way you
do that is with like writing spans so you put like the name inside the spans and then style it
because I want to map over everything
I'm going to use per so I have this like list of continents and this kind of like list of color
palettes and basically for every element in color palette I want to create like some html text
with the name of the color and the name of the continent
so I can use glue to do that and I take my spans from here so inside the span you have style
is equal to so the color is going to be the color palette
dot x so that's going to put in like when you map over it the first time that will give you the first
element in the color palette and then in here I want to get the name of the color palette
and get that first one again
this is something that I would have to templatize for myself like I would have to like yeah put it
somewhere so I could remember how to do it I have a lot of little snippets of like spans
oh yeah for for my own sanity so this gives you like this factor so you have this span and you're
like okay asia but in this color so what I want to do is take that and like construct a sentence
with it I mean you can write out the sentence and pull those values in but you can also use
like string flatten from string r so you can say like between each element put a comma so
the sentence is going to be like asia comma north america comma asia and then you can put a comma
like asia comma north america comma and so on and then but you can change the last one
which is like a really nice feature for writing sentences so that creates this it looks horrendous
which is why you use things like parse so you don't have to type all this out yourself
um but you get like oceana and south america um and then
if I
stick a
little stuff on the end uh it's not gonna like that okay um so this is my subtitle text
so that's gonna be my subtitle colors and then subtitle can be
something like um like twinned cities in
my long list and then full stop okay so my subtitle
yeah that looks all right and then I can stick that in to subtitle with labs so subtitle
equals st and okay you can't see all of them they're a little bit pale so I will probably
want to fix that um but you get this kind of like nice kind of I guess automated colored text
in yeah it says the right thing at least and the right colors it does yeah um and the reason that
works is because in inside the theme I have plot dot subtitle equals element text box simple
which is from gg text and it basically says apply any html formatting or markdown formatting
to the text if you just have like element text um you'll just like get the sort of garbled um
html what I think might help is if I put those names in bold text just for some of those lighter
colors right so you can use like it's something that I think is a little bit weird to combine
markdown formatting with html in the one line um but it works so I will um so you can stick uh
the the names in bold text and in markdown and it just makes it a little bit easier to read
um and then you can go ahead and sort of start adding things uh like titles and captions um
and whatnot um the other thing I want to do is move this down a little bit so in annotate um
you have like h just and v just to move up and down um I can never remember which way around
they are this is where you type it and figure it out actually I love teaching h just and v just
but whenever I'm in some sort of like other coordinate system who knows yeah um so we just
moved it down a little bit so if I go a little bit further okay um it is supposed to be between
like um zero one but putting values outside of that does work um so putting to two does
shift it down a bit um and I think that's that is the benefit of chord radial is that like
moving stuff up and down actually moves it up and down if you use chord polar moving it
up and down like sends it like left and right diagonal yeah which is really confusing um
so we kind of got this chart here um I think what I uh what I would what I kind of want to do this
is because it's it's not super kind of explanatory would we make it um interactive um so the nice
thing so if we put like the let's say we put the city interactive
so switch geom call to geom call interactive and let's say the tooltip is just the city
initially it's not going to do anything because with
with the giraffe package slash functions you have to put it in
uh here and does this work
that's not weird okay
okay that's not working for some reason okay let's ignore that for a second um
what else do I want to do with this okay so the other thing I wanted to check was like does this
actually work in terms of being parameterized so if I switch it to like a different city and just
rerun all of my codes does this work and like it does like you can see that it's the colors are
still like the right way around they're still in the same kind of order nothing's changing but
you're getting this updated chart um which is quite nice so yeah I think like we are starting
to run out of time a little bit so I will yeah but look how far you've come in I know less than
an hour this is amazing um the last couple of things I'll show you is like um I guess like
using like title um so title I might just do something like twinned cities like around the world
um and again I've kind of like pre-populated that plot.title thing
um so it actually uses a different font and like makes it bigger um one of the nice things about
this is like relative sizing um so the idea with using size equals rel is that
it's saying that the title is 1.5 times the base size which means that if you want to resize your
chart you don't have to go through and like change the font size of every single element
um so I think this is like quite small um and my base size and my uh theme is 12 so if I made it a
little bit bigger okay like everything kind of scales up which is quite nice um so I did that
and the other thing I do have is um some functions um so these both I have two functions
here one is like social caption and one is source caption which I appreciate are badly named because
they do quite different things um so these are both currently in a personal R package but what
these do is basically um sort of define the text I usually use in the source um so if I run this
what it does is similar to that kind of um trick we did with the color text as it creates
all of this um like horrendous looking html code um to stick some icons and like
attribution in it and then this um is where I would put like combine the
attribution for the source of data with the attribution for the chart and the source of the
data is um is from wiki data I think yes okay um so let's put that in there
and then if I do in here uh caption equals cap
okay it adds like this at the bottom automatically for me um so I don't have to kind of think about
that every week I sort of figure that that problem out once um and then never do it again
you're so smart only solving your own problems once yeah I try to solve them every week
um yeah um I probably did make this a little bit less tall because I've got one of the things is
when you're using um like chord radial is it sort of like does this fixed aspect ratio of the plot
area to make it square so you end up with this like weird white space um but you can kind of
play around with that actually like 6.5 is probably nice um so yeah I think that's it
yeah and that looks kind of okay and you can like adjust the margins um a little bit yeah
I was just thinking I usually use chord fixed chord underscore fixed but I think that that's
only for cartesian yeah so you can you can do the same sort of thing if you're making something that's
square yeah um then yeah core fixed is is really useful it's really nice for like heat maps when
you're trying to make yeah not as helpful with this situation but we did have a canvas question
if we want to I know we only have like nine minutes left but let's pop it in here Dan Daniel
Chen asked um so you can save a plot with the canvas call and it doesn't mess up the ggplot object
yes you can um that's a very good question um so one I guess there's two ways of thinking about
this is one you can you can either like get rid of your kind of canvas call and like it looks
horrible but then you can do gg save as normal and it will look nice um the quicker way of doing
it is actually the um the ggview package package has has two functions one is canvas the other one
is save ggplot um save underscore ggplot so I this is what actually converted me to being like a
forward assignment um operator um I appreciate that um so I usually have this commented out at
the end of my templates um but this sort of says like assign that to the object p and then you can
save underscore ggplot at the object p and that will save it um in the right place um and it's
quite easy to just comment that little bit out if you decide to make some other tweaks to it
um but I can show you what that looks like oh my gosh look at all the nice little like social
icons down there this is yeah adorable so I did there is a blog post I wrote on like how to make
your own and I think someone um converted that into an r package and I uh I cannot remember the
name of it but it's something like gg like gg annotate or like caption I will look it up and
I will find it um but okay we'll put it in the discord yeah once we find it like when you run um
save ggplot like that's that's what you get um so it looks you know identical to this version here
this which is why I use it what you're getting yeah know what you're getting you don't spend
80s like styling it and making it pretty and then have to like do it all again when you decide what
size your chart is um so that's kind of like a really nice thing with that but yeah so I think
yeah so I think like that's we've done like what like 15 minutes and that's kind of where we are
I think amazing look how far the like helpful tools and you know I hit this problem once I'm
gonna solve it once and have it solved for me and in the future look how far that can get you
that's amazing yeah so like it really saves time doing those like repetitive tasks that you do
over and over like you just save so much time if you don't have to kind of keep doing them um well
we have continually been mind blown in the in the discord over here um it's been amazing
one of the um let me see one of the things I wanted to point out is I said oh it took me this
long to realize that Nicola is like um in our brand was Nicola Reni brand oh yeah and then
someone mentioned that it's also why cow plot is called that because c-o-w was clause o wilk
oh nice blew my mind what a what a great piece of lore um thank you so much for for sharing
everything and all of your wisdom you have some groupies here if people would like to
keep up with you and see your posts what is the best way for them to do that
um I'm on blue sky and pink tin and mastodon or my website which has been there all of the
other things yes and like if you see the strip at the bottom of her her plot there you can see
all of the places to find her there you go there you go all of these places there you go and you
I happen to know submitted this teddy tuesday data you regularly curate so thank you so much
for the the kind of like service that you do to our community and helping curate thank you I
won't fully take credit for this week's curation it was actually a colleague of mine that I worked
with curated the data I just did the pr but the easy way at the end yeah the important part of
getting it across the finish line everybody I would really love to encourage you to curate a
data set we have an entire episode that we did with john harman of tidy tuesday and if you are
curious about how to put data together how to curate it and submit it I really really highly
encourage you to do that it's such a fun process and then your data gets to be used by people all
over the globe as they are learning and practicing their database um which is a really really cool
feeling I have submitted once and I got to see people make plots and I was just like mind blown
other than that Nicola thank you so much for joining us this was super fun I hope you had a
good time you're welcome I had a great time awesome everybody big round of applause for
Nicola big round of applause for Nick who joined us as our special co-host today Isabella we really
really miss you we hope you're having a wonderful time at PyCon and we'll see you all um on Thursday
for coming to the data science hangout or next Tuesday at the lab bye everybody I'll see you on
discord